Guide to the George Mason University photograph collection, 1950s-2007
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
George Mason University photograph collection
1950s-2007
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
R0120
61 linear ft.; 147 boxes
The George Mason University photograph collection is a combination of nine series: University Relations, Broadside Student Newspaper, Yearbook Photographs, George Mason University Foundation, Athletic Department, Office of Admissions, Office of the Registrar, photographs from unidentified offices, and Creative Services. The total collection contains over 12,000 color and black and white photographs, including prints, contact sheets, and negatives, taken between the 1950s and 2007. The collection includes images of student life, campus architecture and construction, campus events, faculty and staff, performances, and art.
Administrative Information
Alternative Form Available
Portions of the GMU photograph collection are available online through Flickr and the GMU Archives Photostream.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the offices of University Life, University Relations, and the GMU Foundation.
Historical Information
The Office of University Relations is the primary communication center and contact point for information about the university. The office leads the university community in promoting George Mason University as a world-class institution of higher education.
Broadside, George Mason University's official student newspaper, began its life as The Gunston Ledger. An eight-page monthly printed on 12 inch by 9 inch paper, The Gunston Ledger first appeared on October 15, 1963 on the then George Mason College campus located in Bailey's Crossroads. On the staff of twelve students included a photography editor, Richard Sparks, and he contributed two to four photos for each edition. The content consisted of campus news, features on GMC faculty and students, engagement and wedding notices, and some commentary. The Ledger became the Broadside on October 28, 1969. It was explained in that issue that the name change was part of an effort to remake the paper into more of a news instrument like that of the nation's revolutionary fathers. The Broadside was a weekly paper which contained sixteen or more pages in each issue. Photography in the Broadside was mostly limited to campus events and personalities. Today, Broadside is a modern newspaper. It is generated via computer and is published in a large, folded newspaper format. With two issues each week, it is produced more frequently. Its news is local, national, and international in scope. Besides campus news, the paper features national and world events, entertainment, music, and restaurant reviews, sports, and commentary. Photography for each issue is provided by both digital and traditional 35mm format cameras. Broadside uses staff photographers and major wire service outlets for its photographs.
As publication of the George Mason University Yearbook ceased in 1988, GM View: The George Mason Video Yearbook was born. Mason had maintained a print version of the yearbook since 1965 under various names (i.e. Advocate, By George, Patriotism, and others). GM View has been in continuous publication since 1989. Though each year's production is different from the others, they all have maintained the same basic format: a length of about 30 minutes; and coverage of university sports, greek, and campus events (such as Mason and Patriots' Day, International Week celebrations, graduations, etc). This digital collection was created with the kind, generous, and expert help from the staff of GMU TV and Digital Programs and Systems, George Mason University Libraries.
The George Mason University Foundation was established in 1966 to advance and further the aims and purposes of George Mason University. It is a 501(c)(3) non-profit foundation organized and operated exclusively for the benefit of the university. The foundation assists the university in generating private support, and manages, invests, and administers private gifts, including endowment and real property. It is governed by a volunteer Board of Trustees, led by a chairman.
Scope and Content
The George Mason University photograph collection is a combination of nine series: University Relations, Broadside Student Newspaper, Yearbook Photographs, George Mason University Foundation, Athletic Department, Office of Admissions, Office of the Registrar, photographs from unidentified offices, and Creative Services. The total collection contains over 12,000 color and black and white photographs, including prints, contact sheets, and negatives, taken between the 1950s and 2007.
Series 1 contains 1696 folders which contain thousands of photographs; estimated to contain 10,000 photogaphs or more. The date range is from 1950s-1999. The series is mostly black and white photographs, contact sheets, and negatives. There are also some color images. Subjects include commencements and graduations as well as campus development from the beginning as Northern Virginia University Center (NVUC) to George Mason University in 1972. The modern university depicted in the photographs from the 1980s-1990s include construction photographs of academic buildings, dormitories, and parking lots. A few events seen throughout the collection are George Mason Day, Patriot's Day, freshman orientation, Alumni Association parties, registration, athletics, student club meetings, art sculputures and displays, GMU Law School, extended studies, Speakers Bureau, Chess Federation, Northern Virginia Press Club, counseling, class trips, dances, festivals, presentations, promotions, donation events, Agora Society, Federal Theatre Project, Wolf Trap, and student productions.
Series 2 contains over two thousand photographs taken between 1971 and 1999. Ninety-nine percent of the photographs were taken by Broadside staff members, while the remaining images comprise official publicity photos of individuals or organizations. Topics in the collection include: images of the campus, student organizations, university sports, campus events, university administrative units, the GMU Board of Visitors, individuals, featured entertainers, restaurants, and arts. The majority of the images are in black-and-white, a few color images are dispersed throughout. The color images are almost all from the 1990s. Some negatives are available for a small part of the collection, found mostly in the sports photographs. Total volume of the collection is 2.75 linear feet.
Series 3 consists of 210 folders which include photographs, contact sheets, and negatives. The images contained in the collection encompass all areas of student life at George Mason University including students on campus, studying, Greek life, athletics, professors, and campus scenery. The date range is from 1979 to the mid-1990s. The total volume is 2.5 linear feet.
Series 4 contains color negatives and slides documenting the 1989 GMU Foundation Fundraising Campaign. The majority of the negatives and slides are images of student life on campus but also campus buildings, arts and performances, faculty, and campus technology. The slides and negatives occupy eleven boxes and span 2 linear feet.
Series 5 consists of photographs from the GMU Athletic Department used in game programs and promotional literature. Subjects include campus life, game crowds, and athletic competitions.
Series 6 includes photographs of office scenes, staff, and social gatherings from the Office of Admissions.
Series 7 consists of slides from graduation ceremonies in 1970 and 1971. These slides originated in the Office of the Registrar.
Series 8 was artificially created with photographs from unidentified offices. Subjects are similar to those from the other series including athletic events, campus life, faculty, and campus buildings.
Series 9 contains thousands of photographs from the Creative Services division of University Relations.
The date range for this series is 1964-2007. The series consists of mostly black and white photographs, contact sheets, slides, and negatives. There are also some color images. Subjects include graduations (commencements) as well as campus development from the 1970s to early 2007. The bulk of the material contains images of faculty, staff, students, alumni, campus scenes, construction, and events. Subjects seen throughout the series include George Mason Day, Patriot's Day, freshman orientation, Alumni Association parties, registration, athletics, student club meetings, art sculputures and displays, GMU Law School and Arlington campus, Prince William campus, Mason community, Chess Federation, Northern Virginia Press Club, Northern Virginia and Washington D.C. scenes, class trips, dances, festivals, presentations, promotions, donation events, the Federal Theatre Project, Wolf Trap, and student productions. This series has many images in common with series one.
There are four subseries to this series based on original order.
The first subseries is Subjects. This subseries contains mostly black and white photographs with some slides, color photographs, negatives, and contact sheets. It is arranged by subject according to a number system employed by the university photographers. The number system is as follows: 1. Outdoor campus and scenics, 2. Buildings and physical features, 3. Construction, 4. Students: Individuals, 5. Students: Groups 6. Students: In classrooms, 7. Students: Non-class academic, 8. On-campus housing, 9. Student services, 10. Student-Faculty interaction, 11. Social events / club activities, 12. Admin/faculty/staff: Individuals, 13. Admin/faculty/staff: Groups, 14. Admin/faculty/staff: Workplace, 15. Admin/faculty/staff: Social/casual, 16. VIP's on campus, 17. Commencement (graduation), 18. Arts Gala, 19. University Day, 20. Miscellaneous annual events, 21. Miscellaneous one-time events, 22. Student performances, 23. Faculty performances, 24. Student artworks/exhibitions, 25. Faculty artworks/exhibitions, 26. Visiting performances/exhibitions, 27. Fine and performing arts classrooms, 28. Science labs, 29. Science field trips, 30. Computer facilities, 31. Cablecast facilities, 32. Nursing School facilities, 33. Law School Facilities (Arlington campus), 34. High-tech centers and firms, 35. Northern Virginia area, 36. Washington D.C. attractions, 37. Patriot Center events (non-GMU), 38. Basketball (GMU), 39. Soccer (GMU), 40. Other varsity sports, 41. Special effects and abstracts, 42. Copy shots, titles and logos, 43. Other off-campus locations, 44. Alumni, 45. Community service/events, 46. Historical/archival photos, 47. Federal Theatre Project (FTP), 48. New Century College, 49. Campus community, 50. Miscellaneous, 51. Prince William, 52. President Alan Merten
Subseries two is Chronological. It is arranged by date from earliest to most recent. This series contains mostly contact sheets and negatives but also includes some black and white photographs, and slides.
Subseries three consists of publications and their accompanying photographs. Formats include black and white photographs, color photographs, slides, negatives, and contact sheets with their corresponding brochures, reports, posters, or newsletters. They are arranged alphabetically.
Subseries four consists of fourteen disassembled photo albums. Photo albums are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Arrangement
Organized into nine series and then sorted either chonologically or alphabetically.
Series 1: University Relations, 1950s-1999 (Boxes 1-37)
Series 2: Broadside, 1971-1999 (Boxes 1-6)
Series 3: George Mason University Yearbook, 1979-mid 1990s (Boxes 1-6)
Series 4: George Mason University Foundation, 1989 (Boxes 1-11)
Series 5: Athletic Department, 1978-1994 (Box 1)
Series 6: Office of Admissions, 1985-1995 (Box 1)
Series 7: Office of the Registrar, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
Series 8: Photographs from Unidentified Offices, 1951-2000 (Boxes 1-3)
Series 9: Creative Services, 1964-2007 (Boxes 38-118)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds the George Mason University archives.
GMU Creative Services online image archives.
Index Terms
Persons:
Fenwick, Charles Rodgers--Photographs.; Miller, Andrew--Photographs.; Holton, Abner Linwood Jr.--Photographs.; Bumgarner, Ken--Photographs.; Buchanan, James--Photographs.; Dalton, John N.--Photographs.; Matsunaga, Spark --Photographs.; Palmer, Ronald --Photographs.; Krug, Robert Charles --Photographs.; Reznor, Trent--Photographs.; Bush, George--Photographs.; Clinton, William--Photographs.; Johnson, George--Photographs.; Reno, Janet--Photographs.; Biden, Joe--Photographs.
Corporate Names:
George Mason University--Photographs.; Alpha Chi--Photographs.; Tau Kappa Epsilon--Photographs.; Phi Delta Kappa--Photographs.; Quintillion Society--Photographs.; GMU Women's club--Photographs.; George Mason Bank--Photographs.
Geographical Names:
Fairfax (Va.)--Photographs
Subjects:
Events--Photographs.; Performance art--Photographs.; Graduation ceremonies--Photographs.; Art--Photographs.; Universities and colleges--Photographs.; People--Photographs.; Police--Photographs.; Dormitories--Photographs.; Restaurants--Photographs.; Sports--Photographs.; Students--Photographs.
Document Types:
Negatives.; Photographic prints.; Slides.
Contents List
- Series 1: University Relations, 1950s-1999; (37 boxes)
  A collection of more than 10,000 black and white photographs, contact sheets, and negatives, taken between the 1950s and 1999, covering George Mason University commencements and graduations, campus developments, events, and performances.
  - Northern Virginia University Center, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Negatives, Prints
  - Bailey's Crossroads, 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Prints
  - Wreath at Jefferson Memorial, April 13, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sign Raising, May 08, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Final Day Exercises, June 06, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First Picnic Gunston Hall, May 16, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Convocation and Honor ceremony, May 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Graduation Final Day, June 06, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Groundbreaking, August 01, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fairfax Campus and Bailey's Crossroads Sign, October 10, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Aerial Photos George Mason College, October 11, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fairfax Campus [Negative-artists rendering], October 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Students, October 13, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fairfax Campus [construction], October 14, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Graduation] Final Day exercises and Memo, October 15, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dr. Reid with UVA GMC sign, October 16, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dedication Day, Fall, October 17, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Contact Sheets, Prints
  - Open House and Miss Katheryn Howell, October 18, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Negatives, Prints, Contact Sheets
  - [Graduation] Final Day, October 19, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Directors Tea, October 20, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Contact Sheets
  - Library construction, October 21, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - George Mason Day, October 22, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Science Night, October 23, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - First Graduating Class, October 24, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Commencement, October 25, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Aerial shots of campus, October 26, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Graduation, October 27, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - George Mason University North Campus, October 28, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Campus construction, October 29, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Campus scenes, October 30, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Northern Virginia development, Dulles airport, October 31, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Aerial shots of campus, November 01, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Eugene C. Paige, Jr., November 02, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Graduation, November 03, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Summer Commencement, November 04, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Arts and Sciences Building Dedication, November 05, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Eugene McCarthy Visit, November 06, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - P.E. Building Construction, November 07, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ordinary Scenes, November 08, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Classroom and General Scenes, November 09, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Classroom photos, November 10, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Campus Classrooms, November 11, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fairfax Women's Club Donation to GMU, November 12, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Governor Holton signing H210, November 13, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - George Mason Day, November 14, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tau Kappa Epsilon Clean-up week, November 15, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Service Awards Ceremony, November 16, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - International Night, November 17, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Quintillion Society Check Presentation, November 18, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Old Fairfax High School Lease Signing, November 19, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Alpha Chi Installation, November 20, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Swearing in of Board of Visitors, November 21, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Graduation, November 22, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Freshman Orientation, November 23, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bus service, November 24, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Susan Romans, November 25, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - George Mason University Night, November 26, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Yoga lecture by "Great Master", November 27, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - General campus photos, November 28, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Negatives, Contact Sheets
  - Chemistry Eternal Fountain, November 29, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - George Mason Painting in George Mason Hotel, Alexandria, November 30, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Coach Linn and Coach Sphuler, December 01, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Science Night, December 02, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Political Panel Debate 8th District, December 03, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Agora Society production "Arms and the Man", December 04, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Registration: Finley Building and Floor, December 05, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Governor's conference, December 06, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Tree planting and Thompson hall, December 07, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Frank Morock [sports information], December 08, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Cheerleaders, December 09, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - GMU gym interior, December 10, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Dance recital, December 11, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Alumni party, December 12, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Library at night, December 13, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Library, December 14, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Christmas tree planting, December 15, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - John Whalen and telescope lens, December 16, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Eric Christenson editor Broadside, December 17, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Jay Jarvis Student Government President, December 18, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Football on quad, December 19, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Ordinary scenes, December 20, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Winter Commencement (no campus auditorium), December 21, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Dr. Michael Kelley English Department, December 22, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Women weightlifting, December 23, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Women in Literature" class, December 24, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - President Thompson "portrait" in academia regalia, December 25, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Student Union construction, December 26, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - North Campus-building, cafeteria, kitchen, December 27, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Negatives
  - Mrs. Virginia Austin, December 28, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Forensics, December 29, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Groundbreaking-Academic IIA, Library, December 30, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Graduate math class, December 31, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Jorge Ponce-Cuban guitarist, GMU student, January 01, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Biology class (for graduate catalog), January 02, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Indian Dancer, January 03, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photos for catalog, January 04, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Roy Anderson, January 05, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Dr. Sundell-Chairman English Department, January 06, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Graduate Education Class (Dr. Montebello), January 07, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Dr. V. Dykstra, January 08, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dr. V. Dykstra-announcement as president of GMU, January 09, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - GMU Day, January 10, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Modern Dance for Arts Festival, January 11, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Forensics Team to Nationals, January 00, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Black Awareness week, April 17, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - International Night Promo, April 18, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Trish Milford and Chris Collins-forensics team, April 18, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Black Awareness fashion show, April 18, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Modern Dance Concert-promo, May 03, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Athletic banquet, May 12, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Government biennium budget visit, May 21, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Construction pictures, May 16, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Student Government awards banquet, May 23, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Nursing faculty-Dr. Evelyn Cohelan, May 23, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Spring Commencement, May 25, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Flags, July 01, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Dykstra assuming office, July 02, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Dr. Robert Hawkes, July 05, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Dr. Ralph Baxter-assistant provost, July 05, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Rudy Jones and summer recreation clinic, July 05, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - William Snavely, July 06, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Architecture of GMU, July 09, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - French students tour campus with J. Gurfein and Willis, July 10, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Presidents house, August 02, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Summer Commencement, August 11, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Campus, Summer 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Charlotte Wilhelmi-Consortium [Assistant to Dean Brundage], August 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Heating and cooling plant construction, September 5-9, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - GMU Night, September 05, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Library construction, September 06, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Pan Hellenic scholarship awards, September 12, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Forensic team, September 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cookbook-GMU Women's club, September 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Students and campus, September 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lab classes, October 04, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mason-Dixon lettermen, October 04, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Dr. George Moseley's East Asia panel discussion, October 08, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Chess tournament, October 09, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Business Honor Society dinner Dr. Giovaccini, October 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Thompson Hall, October 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Louise Lowe [Assistant to President, Executive Secretary Board of Visitors, Affirmative Action], November 01, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Fairfax Young Career Woman, Laura Derr, English Department, November 02, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Library, November 03, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Agora Society play "Skin of Our Teeth", November 05, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Graduate faculty council, November 06, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Red Cross class, November 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Law school announcement, November 01, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Heating and cooling plant construction, December 05, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Telescope progress with John Whalen, December 05, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)